[Music]
hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and welcome to holotalk the internet's
laser and holography talk show enjoyed
in over 42 countries throughout the
world and now here's this week's show
[Music]
Frank hello Howard how are you I'm fine
it was my caller ID oh that's good glad
to hear it's working
your email a little bit earlier on
saying you are available today so I
thought I'd give you a call excellent
excellent
so why don't we start off with having
you tell the listeners a little bit
about the Polaris research group is this
your company yes it is it's a very
impressive website with the pictures of
your lab there I
am glad
you had a very nice thing
when we put the website up because we're
not HTML people we discovered that
depends on which viewer you bring it up
in as to how good it looks yeah but um I
I appreciate the compliment certain
ly we're for those people who've seen
some script on the website we're going
to
yeah we've uh we've got a really very
slap facility
and um
short story on Polaris is that I spent
about 15 years working for the Navy
and uh
laser and Optical applications things
like fiber optic sensors but the big
deal was uh Optical non-destructive
testing
um
flash ahead after 15 years of doing all
sorts of things that were deeply
classified and when they Declassified my
work in
three after
math bought the entire Laboratory wow
and um so we had this you know you know
state-of-the-art laboratory and uh
very nice space
where we've been for the last 13 years
now
and we're one of the two Labs actually
offering uh holographic interferometry
service here in this country it's very
big in Europe
and uh you know very uh very well used
in fact virtually every automotive
company Aerospace manufacturer
it regularly
still something of a
of an odd application here in the U.S
I'm not sure
precisely why that is so I'm something
of an Evangelical about both
Hall and general and holographic
interferometry specifically
so what are what are some of the current
competing Technologies with the
holographic method for interferometry
that's out on the market today well
there aren't a lot actually
of course holography is full
and with current technology that's out
there you can do extreme
extreme sub wavelength measurement
s so you've got something that's
fulfilled real time
and can also be set you
easily or asynchronously to pulse along
with
the motion object it's really just
a really accurate measure
for looking at displacement
around playing there are a number of
that use a similar Concepts similar
physics do developing a clearance map
but the beauty of holography is that it
shows you the
SE placement of the entire object and
the
of that motion so the real point to it
is that once you've stressed an object
however that stress has been applied you
can see what it's doing uh there aren't
a lot of other methods that do that now
there are certainly
methods even some Optical ones
vibrometry and that kind of thing there
are certainly
other ways to measure
stressfully
acquire applying some kind of
and there are other methods of looking
at either defects
or
you know surface
sonography
scanning that kind of thing and many
other methods
but holography is unique and
you can entirely non-contact as far as
the
knee and
the nicest advantage of it is that you
see what is the truth rather than what
is a model and that's the important
thing because the holographic maps are
what's really going on in the real world
as a result of whatever the applied
stress is
I know Newport research at one time had
a catalog it was actually
just a it featured different techniques
that could be done with their laser and
holography system that they put out and
they had a very simple experiment for
holographic interferometry in there
where they used I believe a Coca-Cola
can or something like that that's
correct we've never banned around it
yeah that goes back many many years I
still have that catalog I was one of
their uh one of their first customers in
1980 . oh didn't
the guys that started out uh in in the
kitchen or something wasn't it right Dr
Milton Chang was eventually the uh
president and CEO and
um uh once the company
is going of course uh Milton who is you
know very well known in the optical
community of course she writes every
month in laser focus world
um
he's a brilliant entrepreneur
stellar
ability and of course when he left
Newport research here I'm talking about
Dr Chang but he went on to to found
very
very well known and then successfully
went on and I I know that he's also with
a a
so Dr Chang did tremendous tremendous
things early on as as champion of
holography
so we got to know each other quite
quite time ago
and as a result of that when I was
purchasing
large amounts of equipment from Newport
research and uh though not trying to
to
promulgate one company as a supplier
over the other uh certainly at that time
Newport was you know the only game in
town for the best in the world and
and their holographic camera
which was a brilliant device developed
it's still
an extreme
extreme of the
the company stopped supporting it and
a decade ago
I still use the every day in my lab it's
25 years able to have several of them
they use a photothermal plastic plate
which means you can make a hologram in
under 45 seconds is it still possible
plates I got an email not too long ago
from someone looking for those plates
um there's probably a lot of us out
there looking for plates I recently
found
a
Surplus company
a supply of those plates
okay and um
when they pop up sometimes on eBay
sometimes other places
those of us who see it
generally
either right away to get them
because that camera is still
the one that's most used in the world
there have been other devices out there
and one or two that were actually quite
promising but unfortunately they weren't
able to to be supplied in any
uh quality based quantity
this country so so I still use the
news every day and when it does get to
the point where those plates run out
fortunately I still have a decent Supply
um we're gonna have to go to some other
method and of course now there are other
holographic method s including some that
are photorefractive crystal based
and those are showing very great promise
and there
uh supplying equipment that are
on photorefractants and other Optical
techniques and do the very same thing
yeah this was actually research in a
student at the University
so
maybe if I get another request in the
future I can just send them over to you
and if the price is right maybe you can
part with one of them I think that it's
certainly possible but I wouldn't hold
up hold up promise that really you know
it's kind of the price greater than
rubies I see for those of us who use it
every day it's it's right now the only
tool
uh for that sort of thing because in
order to make holographic interferometry
and
the uh
affordable thing
that's that's one of the important
aspects
expect to do because back in the 70s
when we
were doing what holographers do in
general a film plate or film or a plate
rather of course you said
exposure develop bleach all that stuff
and then come back a little while later
to find out if your hologram was good
you could spend the whole day just to
find out you had a bad inter program
yeah
uh having an insta
system was a real godsend so back in
1980 we did that and we married that to
back then very simple videos
and were able to look at things real
time now of course with you know digital
Imaging uh
pretty sophisticated stuff going on and
so we we do an awful lot of work for
large corporations
everything from vibration of turbine
rotors to uh tiny little component
larger structures
I'm working with a teacher to get their
students involved with holographic
interferometry and
get building balsa wood bridges
and then doing Holograms of them and
placing
fishing tackle weights on them to notice
the stress
stress and see which one of the bridge
designs handles the stress best oh yeah
so terrific application I mean as far as
a career would go or something how many
companies out there are actively doing
holographic interferometry now in the
United States
only a very small handful and the
companies that are doing it are
generally doing it internally uh
aircraft corporations for instance
especially in their defense related
projects they do have capabilities of
doing this uh you know Boeing Northrop
Chrome and that kind of thing
but e
ve outside Consultants at times
but there aren't a lot of companies
where you can just go and be a
hologographer
um Polaris and we're a very small
company
we're sole proprietorship I'm the one
that's in the lab most of the time
they're really only five of us and each
of us has a
stuff I'm pretty much the
other guys are
guys um
and you know we all work together and
depending on the project
but uh for the most part
oh yeah optically related work in the
laboratory and there are not a lot of
other places in the US doing that I
suspect there are a few that uh still
actually off service
um
but um I believe that
it's a pretty hard thing to find in this
country there are equipment
manufacturers oems
in Europe that not only Supply equipment
but offer the service as well it's very
different over there it's very very
strange
what lasers do you have there well a
number
uh
one of the old lexell Model 95 argon
lasers and it's you know you know set up
a single free remote operation
it's a five watt laser
there's a lot of power out of that
uh one of the old Spectra physics sp125
50 million bikinis classic yeah it is
and it's It's actually an incredibly
good laser when it's set up with an
alarm for what it is
um a number of smaller solid state red
ones which
oddly enough nowadays have set up
correctly and thermally controlled
correctly
programs
so depending on
here but my primary laser right now is
uh one of the coherent Compass lasers
okay great unit
it's a great unit as well oh it really
is you know at 532 it's dead stable
we're using 100 milliwatt unit and uh
it's
about the size of a package of
cigarettes plugs into the wall if you
heat sink it correctly then you've got
something that you know has a beautiful
Lifetime and runs stable forever and
makes great Holograms I just acquired a
lexel 88.
the only difficulty is that there were
two configurations of the power supply
one was your standard desktop type of
power supply for lack of a better term
and the other one was the medical based
power supply where the laser head was
actually contained within the cabinet so
I'm having a difficult time trying to
figure out this this
cabinet the power supply cabinet that
runs is about the size of a small filing
cabinet and I had to get a truck to pick
it up because I couldn't even fit it in
the car so I've got to figure out how to
get that all set up but I think that Lex
L88 is a nice laser too oh yeah
yeah I see you're in Cleveland Ohio we
should let the listeners know that yeah
do you ever open your doors to visitors
absolutely we do anytime uh when we
receive
uh one of the things that happens very
regularly uh before anybody
works with us is we'll generally have a
meeting and uh
facilities the laboratory itself is the
Optics lab as you can see on the website
it's about 500 square foot facility very
nice
laboratory environment very well suited
to Optics and and of course we're
we're in a large Industrial
and it's actually
and it's a
facility so we have the
it's part of our
use all of the conference facilities
and even their cafeterias so it was
really pretty nice for us so we've got a
great facility when we bring people in
to visit
sometimes standing in the dark looking
at colored lights later on it sounds
like one of the incubator units is that
what it is that's provided through
General Electric no it's it's really not
the plant we're in here is the where
General Electric has its quartz melt
facility where they make
quartz for virtually all of their
worldwide operations so they have these
huge films that are running uh you know
24 7 30 5 making
pools of quartz roughly three feet thick
and it's across wow
you know for all the different
applications
but this is where we do holography of
all sorts and uh you know of course also
do our work with uh uh you know
Distributing ultimate
what brought that on to uh distribute
ultimate emulsions
this is actually you know one of the
most exciting things for us right now
um as most holographers will probably
don't they
show right now
um
France over the last 20 years uh has
been one of the most brilliant
holographers anywhere in the world
nothing short of miraculous
and I've always been incredibly
impressed with the things he produced
and he was supplying uh a very
Innovative set of emotions
he developed in his own Laboratories
over the last 20 years
those emotions were available only in
Europe they were not available here in
the U.S for a myriad of reasons
including
via standard
container ship the breakage was
horrendous plates so it was very
uneconomical of course the reason
when they transship by air virtually
everything was x-rayed regardless of
what the packaging would say
so it was kind of not a good thing to
have photographic materials being
x-rayed yeah
very short
when uh International manufacturing was
uh developed in Canada which is
one of the major manufacturing
facilities for ultimate emotions is
uh was moved to North America
the manufacturer and uh
for a distributor here in the United
States
and our reputation
was such that they spoke with us
and very excited to be able to become
the US distributor for these
and uh
work with them so what we do
courses whether it's on a website or
direct communication
we will take orders we will have the the
emotions custom
from date of order to date
to daily no more than four weeks every
now and then we do have something in
stock as well
but the nature of nature of the emotion
is that our customers can
but they want
including you know these Wells
like that and the Emulsion itself is
spectacular it is without a doubt the
holographic
in the world it
is the highest resolution
and
if one is to take a look at some of the
corroborative data on the website
where it's just
just Harrison hasn't been the normal
operating specs and it's not a it's not
a negative comment on on other emotions
out there because many of them have
worked just fine over the years
but um it's like anything if you have uh
you know a hand-built hand-tuned sports
car that is compared to you know a
general pickup truck there's going to be
a performance
and we are incredibly pleased to be able
to offer this to holographers at a very
reasonable price
make no bones about it it costs a little
more
and exactly what to do
coupled with the fact that
uh Evian Ted also developed a very
unique
unique set of chemistries
plates
it's a two-part developing system
developer in a bleach
uh very different
than anything that that has been used
before and my own experience with this
over
and of course once I started working
with it regularly
it's just nothing like it in the world
the results are spectacular and when
we're talking about looking at the
Holograms that are virtually without
halation without
without any
any fuzz or noise
you really can make Holograms even in a
student environment that are
indistinguishable from the real object
so I take it the formulations of the
developer not a lot of toxicity to it
that's cool
are extremely low toxicity they are
vastly different than commercial
developers bleaches and um and fixers
and in fact whereas in a normal
photographic process that's exactly what
you have it's developer and then a
gouache and then a bleach and then a
wash and then a
a
fixer
uh this is only a two-part system and it
only takes a few minutes and it's
extremely well defined and the the
plates themselves have a remarkable
sensitivity
so yeah it's
a very low toxic
because in fact when we uh did all of
the necessary paperwork for the
registration
of
the chemistry with
With Friends the US government and ocean
all of that
um we've got a a very nice
nice set of ratings
ratings allow us to ship this
thing which one of the emotions do you
have in stock the most
well if someone were to go to your web
page in order to today Are there
specific emotions within this range that
you have in stock that you can ship
right away
um yeah generally the the no wavelength
ship Reds and greens and it depends on
the size of the plate
um usually the four by fives are what
most people
quickest to acquire and in fact we even
offer a little what we call test kits
where we Supply uh five four by five
plates uh in the wavelength of your
choice
developer and like
and uh
a very nice little kit for
I think it's 129 dollars yeah I'm
actually going to order one of those
from you how terrific yeah order right
on the website we do have secure
shopping cart
and one can make a credit card order
right there and you know secure socket
layering and all of that so it's
extremely high and or you can just
work that out and if you'd like to do
that I recommend it anyway for all our
customers
and this is this is the plug for all of
you out there who are making Holograms
using regular photographic media
media currently available emulsions uh
do give this a try it will be worth your
time it will be worth your money and you
will find that it's something that gives
you
you have never seen
so there's the Shameless plug for the
material because it really is remarkable
and the reason that Polaris is
Distributing it and that we are not only
standing behind it but
is that I've been an active holographer
for three years
and you don't even say I'm 30 years old
I appreciate that uh
68 on the floor of a bedroom oh come on
really I was in high school yeah yeah I
saw my first hologram in 68 but I was in
junior high so we're pretty probably
pretty close in age
yeah so it's not the same generation
yeah I noticed on your web page that
uh for on the ordering page you do have
the eight nanometer they're listed but I
don't see the 15 nanometers this
continued to 15. oh really yeah uh
because you know we're really very
simple
almost the same sensitivity within a
very close percent
um and there was no reason to offer
something that was virtually the same
sensitivity
sent and
and half the resolution okay so we just
went to manufacturing the eight
nanometer for all wavelengths
and we are working on even
their grain
right now and um the the results are
very promising but right now an eight
nanometer Emulsion is certainly the
finest grain by far
and with the sensitivities that we are
we are
demonstrating
again utterly remarkable result
from my point of view you know I can't
say enough that uh
development process
uh that Eve went through to put these
emotions together
uh from my point of view as a
holographer rather than just a supplier
of this material we're nothing short of
Genius
I've never seen anything like this
anywhere I've seen pictures and photos
of his color work which is just
sounding yeah and I would love to see
one in person
the
photographs even on the website
uh just cannot possibly do it justice
seeing these Holograms in person whether
they're the
the Holograms of butterflies or the
Pharaoh or any of the other things that
we've done including the work we've done
in our own Labs both in Canada and here
in Cleveland
um making a hologram
is so simple and in fact we work with
people especially students who buy it
because
make a 10
hologram
and uh it's it's the quickest way
to uh to get really good holographic
results you know to make
to exactly how holography works and then
when you set up regular off-axis system
and you know do all of the uh necessary
uh beam balancing and adjusting and all
of that you can get something incredible
results as well but uh the uh the work
that we've done in our own Laboratories
are really really astonishing
incredibly happy about having this
material
just hope of course that people
everywhere will start using it because
it's only this year that it's become
available in the United States we are
supplying it to a number of uh regular
clients
both industrial and private
and we as they say welcome inquiries we
we'd love to work with more uh we can
make make the material and Supply it in
quantities of course we can all
you can also very large plates for the
through display holography company and
in fact we are doing that very
successfully
largest plates
uplift the
well-known display holography uh
companies out there well I'll certainly
have a a link to your website on
us along with a contact email address
where people can contact you excellent
and since we're running up on 30 minutes
do you happen to have anything you'd
like to add that we haven't spoken about
yet
well I think that the best things that
holography itself has become such a
curiosity over the years and remained
such curiosity over the
over these that are ubiq
in our everyday life as the laser has
become
so I would like to say that Polaris here
in Cleveland
very happy work with anybody from the
student level to the professional level
we're rather extremely experienced over
the last 30 years or so and always
welcome new challenges
we very much want to continue being
Evangelical about both the technical and
descriptive uses of holography and the
display uses of
particularly
energy holographers have the best and
most consist emotions out there and
that's what we're supplying that's great
on I'll come visit you I get out to
Columbus Ohio every spring
well we're two hours North yeah so I'll
have to uh this spring when I head out
to Columbus I head to that I don't know
if you're aware of it or not that Arnold
Classic oh yeah sure yeah I head to the
Arnold Classic every year and uh
drive up and spend an extra day and just
drive up and visit Polaris oh I'd love
it that would be absolutely terrific we
could do another show live from the
floor wow that would be excellent yeah I
do have to say also that
that holography is is what it is
that uh everything you've been doing
over the years with Hollow talk and
instructions and all of the things
you've supplied over the years
such a
both the technology of holography and
the the hobby of holography and the
technical development of people who
decide to go into holography
even though I say I'm an Evangelical
about it uh you are too in your own way
and that's a really wonderful thing so
I'm really happy to have the opportunity
to talk on the
years well thank you that's very kind to
say to say what I do is I just bring the
experts on the show I'm not an expert
myself so well enough to make it
all right well Howard we should probably
close up so that we can keep our file
size and it was very good talking to you
but if you don't hear from me today
you'll probably hear from me tomorrow
because I have to do a little running
around after I get this finished
I'll probably sit down with a cup of tea
tonight and do some editing and get the
announcement out okay terrific all right
that is great thank you very much for
being on the show and taking the time I
really appreciate your taking the time
to talk with me all right take care
Howard